Guide to the Lester Afflick Papers ca. 1975-1998 MSS.097
Fales Library and Special Collections
Lester Afflick Papers
ca. 1975-1998
Fales Library and Special Collections
Afflick, Lester, 1956-2000
MSS.097
7 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Lester Afflick was a downtown poet, writer and once co-editor of 'The Door Newsletter.' The collection is an assemblage of his writings and biographical material which illustrate aspects of his style and the downtown scene in general of the 1990's.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions. Please contact the Fales Library & Special Collections for more information and to schedule an appointment, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Provenance
The Lester Afflick papers were a gift of the Lester Afflick estate. They were initially sorted by friends of Lester Afflick.
Biographical Note
Lester Afflick was a downtown poet, writer and once co-editor of 'The Door Newsletter.' The collection is an assemblage of his writings and biographical material which illustrate aspects of his style and the downtown scene in general of the 1990's. Afflick died of a heart attack in 2000.
Scope and Content Note
The Lester Afflick papers are comprised mostly of correspondence and manuscripts of his poetry.
SERIES DESCRIPTIONS
Series 1: Correspondence contains correspondence to and from Afflick. It is arranged in chronological order with the exception of a folder of correspondence with Martin Afflick.
Series 2: Manuscripts consists of three subseries.
Missing Title
Subseries A contains materials and drafts of Afflick's poetry. They are arranged alphabetically according to a comprehensive list provided by Afflick.
Subseries B contains materials from poetry collections and projected collections. The last folder contains a comprehensive list of Afflick's poems.
Subseries C contains materials manuscripts of plays, essays, and articles.
Subseries D contains disks of Afflick and printouts from those working disks.
Series 3: Biographic Materials contains a small number of biographic materials such as copies of Afflick's birth certificate, announcements, immigration papers, and scrapbooks.
Series 4: Afflick's Personal Library consists of periodicals in Afflick's collection including The Door Newsletter of which he was a co-editor. This series also includes manuscripts of other poets' works.
Arrangement
Folders arranged chronologically or alphabetically depending on the nature of the series. Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Poetry is arranged alphabetically by title.
The files are grouped into 4 series.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Manuscripts
Series III: Biographic Materials
Series IV: Works by Other Writers/Poets
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Poets, American -- 20th century.; Drawings; Correspondence.; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Downtown writers.; Magazines (Periodicals); New York (N.Y.).; Literature, Experimental.; Manuscripts for publication.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1975 - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1991 - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - correspondence [n.d.], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Martin Afflick correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Manuscripts
  - Subseries A: Poems
    - "Abiding" - "Always", undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Amulet" - "At Present, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Back at the Reader" - "Black Moon", undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Black, White" - "By the Side of the Road", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Cafe" - "Childhood", undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Chill in the Air" - "Curtains", undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Dance" - "Dust", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Early" - "Ex-Priestess", undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Face Down" - "Few Days", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Fiesta" - "Fuel", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Galleon" - "Gypsy Prayer", undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Habitations" - "Here", undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Hibiscus, Lime, Palm" - "Hurry", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "I" - "I Do Like to Doom", undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "I Dream About You Baby" - "I Set Out for Islands", undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "I Shall Whisper" - "If This Is a Poem", undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "I'm a Man" - "In the Desert", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "In the Evening" - "Island", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Island Wild Breezes" - "I've Looked Too Long", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "J. B. Token..." - "Koa", undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "L. A." - "Little Eyes", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Little Green Apples" - "Lovesong", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Mad" - "Mexican Landscape", undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Midday Walk with Hills" - "My Understanding", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Naked" - "No", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "No Bird" - "Nocturne", undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Nod to the Night" - "Now on the Balcony", undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Observation After the Fact" - "On the Balcony", undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - On the Eve of Another... - "Outside the Fashion", undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Painter Is a Fool - "Pharoh", undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Photograph - "Poem Song", undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Poems to a Dancer - "Pubs", undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Raoul - "Ruined Temple", undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - She Is Dancing - "Small Song", undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Smoking - "Sometimes", undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Somewhat Like a Goddess... - "Story", undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - The Street Is Littered - "Survivalist", undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "The Table at the Bar" - "There Are No Birds", undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "There Are No Temples" - "They Wooded", undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "They Were There" - "This Strange City", undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "This Wanton Night" - "Trail", undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Train" - "Two Gods", undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Uncalibrated" - "Urn Myself", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Vacation" - "Vodka", undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Waiting There" - "Westbound", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Western Haiku" - "Winter Sky", undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Wiseass" - "World Is a Ghetto", undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "Yawning" - "The Zen Way Out, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Handwritten manuscripts of poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Handwritten manuscripts of poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Handwritten manuscripts of poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Handwritten and untitled manuscripts of poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Handwritten and untitled manuscripts of poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Handwritten and untitled manuscripts of poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Subseries B: Poetry Collections
    Note on Folder Numbering
    In March 2009, folder numbers in Box 4 were changed. For citation purposes, the changes are tracked below:
    Subseries B, Folders 1 - 10: no change. Subseries C: former folder 1 is now 11 former folder 2 is now 12 former folder 3 is now 13 Subseries D:
    former folder 1 is now 14 former folder 2 is now 15 former folder 3 is now 16 former folder 4 is now 17 former folder 5 is now 18 former folder 6 is now 19 former folder 7 is now 20 former folder 8 is now 21 former folder 9 is now 22
    - Under the Almond Trees (Complete Manuscript), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Under the Almond Trees (Incomplete Manuscript), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Lester in Brooklyn, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Lester in Brooklyn, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Lester in Brooklyn, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Lester in Brooklyn, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Lester in Brooklyn, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Untitled Book Project, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Untitled Book Project, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Lists of Poems, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Subseries C: Essays, plays, and articles
    - Plays, Stories, and Essays, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Articles, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Untitled Projects, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Subseries D: Disks and printouts of disks
    - Computer disks, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Computer disks, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Computer disks, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Computer disks, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Printout of disk 1 - (Under the Almond Trees), undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Printout of disk 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Printout of disk 3A, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Printout of disk 3B, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Printout of disk 4, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Series III: Biographic Materials
  - I. N. S. Correspondence and papers, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Birth certificate, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Announcements, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Addresses and phone numbers, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Misc. biographic materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Scrapbook/notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Series IV: Works By Other Writers/Poets
  - The Door Newsletter, undated (Box 7a, Folder 1)
  - Appearances, undated (Box 7a, Folder 2)
  - Forty Pounds of Salt, undated (Box 7a, Folder 3)
  - Harelquin Sound Productions, undated (Box 7a, Folder 4)
  - Manhattan Poetry Review, undated (Box 7a, Folder 5)
  - NYS Waterways Project, undated (Box 7a, Folder 6)
  - Poetry in Performance, undated (Box 7a, Folder 7)
  - Poetry in Performance, undated (Box 7a, Folder 8)
  - Poetry in Performance, undated (Box 7a, Folder 9)
  - Youth Magazine, undated (Box 7b, Folder 10)
  - Other poets' manuscripts, undated (Box 7b, Folder 11)
  - Showcase at Sweeny's, undated (Box 7b, Folder 12)
  - Drawings/illustrations, undated (Box 7b, Folder 13)
  - Articles on artists, undated (Box 7b, Folder 14)